Hi everyone. I want to welcome
to the second New York Haskell meetup
It is a great crowd just like last time
Thank everyone for coming, it was a great...
holiday party yesterday
I just want to make two quick pitches
First is we've got a great crowd but
there's room for more so if you know
people that would be interested in
coming, publicity is great.
We want to promote our great language
Number two, um... we're lining up a lot
of good talks but it's always good to
have as many talks is possible lined up
so if you are interested in giving a
talk be it a small talk, a long talk
on just a little project you did or you
know a lot more sort of lengthy
presentation um...
talk to myself .. That is Rich Minerich
in the back there, he is one of
the organizers of the Haskell meet up as well
Doug is up here. If you want to
stand up and wave "hi," so people know who
the organizer are who they could talk to about
whatever they want
Ryan is
somewhere and um... yes
That's one, two, three, four uh...
Am I forgetting.. Oz! but he's not
here.. is he here tonight?
Okay, so those are the organizers.
Come talk to us if you want to present or
about anything else.
And now i'm going to introduce Ed Kmett.
Edward Kmett who is a co-worker
of mine at Standard and Poor Capital I_Q_
He's written a zillion and one
libraries and uh...
he discovered with the lens library
that if he added documentation
that he got a lot more users! So this
is actually rapidly acquiring
a reputation and finding widespread
use and it's really cool, so he
going to tell us all about it.
Thank you, Ed.
I'm going to waffle back and forth
between
some slides that I have that have a
lot of the theory and motivation
like from a technical standpoint
for lenses
and just like a G_H_C_I_ session where
I'll use them in practice so that
even if you're having trouble following along
with the theory and the derivation
you can see them used
and get a feel for how you'd use them in
your own Haskell code. All right?
So, um...
I've got a lot of material to cover today.
So I'm going to ramble on for
a couple of hours. I apologize.
So I guess the first question is:
What is a lens?
In imperative code you can very easily
read and write to like nested getters and setters
way down in a hierarchy.
I can call "foo . bar . baz . quux" and "+= 10"
and I don't really
think too hard about violating what.. what the
Eiffel guys call the Law of Demeter
and going down and accessing properties
of properties of properties.
In a functional setting it's a lot
harder to do that though, because
I have to.. maybe I use record syntax and
I have to go in and
it costs me more and more, because I
have to keep talking about the same objects
to go deeper and deeper.
So, record updates are not very
compositional.
um...
and so PLT Borat based on.. actually I
think a version of a talk Tony gave
on lenses..
Tony Morris
said something to the effect that
costate comonad coalgebras are the equivalent of
Java's variable update technology for Haskell
And that
is really .. if you take nothing else away
from what a lens is
it's getters and setters, we just
smash them together into
some kind of object.
So simplest form of a lans that we might
make would be to pair
the getter let's call it "view" here
with a setter
so we will get an "a" out of an "s"
and we'll set
taking an "s"
and a new "a" that we want to replace into it
and well give you a new "s".
Okay? And we want to put some common
sense laws on these.
Okay? We can actually drive these laws
about four or five different ways
and they all give you the same laws so that
kind of gives us
a hint that we're onto the right abstraction
and one is is that if i "get" something
out of my "whole"
and i put it back
it's the same as if i didn't do anything,
so a lens has no other effects.
Right? It doesn't bump a counter somewhere
inside the object, it doesn't do
anything like that.
All I can do is read and write to part of it.
And if I put something in, I have
to be able to get back out.
Okay? And finally, if i "set" twice.. I
set it to something and i set it to
something else, it's just like I did the
second setting. The first setting didn't matter
So these three laws let us reason
about code that uses lenses.
I gave an answer on stack overflow that
goes on for hundreds of lines about this
using this exact formulation of lenses.
We're not going to be using this kind
of lens today.
[laughter]
um...
it goes so far and then stops.
So, to talk about that
costate comonad coalgebra,
just long enough to throw it away:
So what that means is is that if we were
to take this definition
they both start with an "s" and so I
could theoretically just these two
functions together into one function.
I give you a function that
gives you back a pair
of the "a" to "s" and the "a".
Right? And that construction on the end
happens to be the store comonad
or the costate comonad
if you want to go about it from a
theoretical perspective.
and this is a store comonad coalgebra
and the laws to be a comonad coalgebra
in this case are exactly the lens laws
that we just stated.
Okay? So that is a completely different
way to give the exact same laws.
I think that the common sense version
makes more sense.
This one is also in this is uh...
the approach that I used
in my data-lens library.
That was the lens library that I used to
sell everybody before this one.
I handed off maintainership on that and then I
subsequently stabbed poor Russell in the back
by implementing a new lens library
[laughter]
So this is like if we were to look
at the version inside of
data-lens
but the only reason why I wanted to point to this
is that you can build a category
for these, where you can compose these.
The Category class basically says that
you have (.) which lets you
compose things kind of like functions.
"You can compose arrows in the category."
and that there is an identity arrow for
every object
There will not be a test on this code.
We're not going to use it.
The problem with this approach is that
somebody has to remember to
import Control.Category
They have to hide a couple of
things from the Prelude.
uh...
What I want to do is I want to write
lenses that I don't need
to go off to Control.Category and grab id and (.)
and along the way we're going to get some
extra stuff for free.
I was holding this up as kind of a straw man.
All right.
So there is a um...
This is a reference to a talk that was given
by Eric Meijer
..probably ten years ago..
about a bunch of language features that
eventually became um...
LINQ inside of C#
and it is what we need
I haskell we often have -- there's an idiom that
we use over and over again
that you'll see in
certainly people's code ... that is,
like, if we start with like say dot here
I can work with dot dot dot
okay and now it's like dot goes into
a function of one argument.
"(.) . (.)" will go into
two functions deep. Right?
"(.) . (.) . (.)"
will go three functions deep.
So, as many dots as I compose here
I am going to nest that many arguments
in the function.
This is um..
I believe Conal Elliott called them
semantic editor combinators and he
gave them all sorts of fancy names.
Uh... we can do this with "fmap".
instead of functions, because
the definition of
fmap for the function functor
for a function from "a" or whatever.
uh... is fmap
rather, fmap is (.).
we can generalize this pattern
and say, "well, I can go go and instead of
going with fmap where I can go under
one functor
I can go under two or three.
"fmap" or "fmap . fmap" or "fmap . fmap . fmap".
Okay?
Interestingly,
The order of these arguments is kind of
reversed from what you'd expect as I'm
taking
upon function from "a" to "b"
to a function from ah..
"f a" to "f b". Er.. Lets go here:
A function from "a -> b" to a function
from "f a -> f b".
and so
each one of the is
the dot is actually reading backwards
from the way you would
come at it from a Haskell perspective.
Er.. as you'd think about it from a Haskell
perspective usually.
So these are semantic editor combinators and...
Conal gave these all sorts of fun names.
We have "result" was dot, and "element" was
"fmap" and "second", and you can compose
"element . result . second" and
walked down
in for
editing assignments and what not
uh... I'm going to make an alias for this
just for sake of discussion, because this is going
to be the same pattern for aliases
I'm going to use
for the kind of lenses that I want.
and so
a semantic editor combinator
is going to say given an "s"
and a function from "a" to "b"
I can give you a "t"
So this is like fmap
Right? If this was "f a" and this was "f b"
this would be the signature of "fmap".
But also "fmap . fmap" firts this pattern,
because I didn't actually prejudge that this
had the shape "f a"
"s" could be lots of different things.
So "fmap . fmap" is a semantic editor combinator.
and "fmap . fmap . fmap" or
"result . element . second . first"
All of these would be valid semantic editor combinators.
And if you look at "fmap",
"fmap" is then a semantic editor combinator
that says
given "f a" and a function from "a" to "b", I
can give you an "f b"
You can just put a different signature on it.
Right? Because this expands to the existing definition of "fmap".
er.. the existing signature.
and then "first" will
walk over the first element of a pair.
which while, this guy is obvious not a "functor"
you know in the capital "F" sense of "Functor"
but it still has that same kind of
functoriality of it.
It's just the functor over
the first half of a pair.
given a pair of "a" and "c"
and a function from "a" to "b",
I can give you a pair of "b" and "c"
So this leads us to the first
construction that we're gonna deal with
in the lens library that is not a lens.
We will talk about setters.
So, the same way that we built, er..
that we can compose dots
in series and we can compose "fmap"s in series
uh... these these are an idiom that a lot
of people know in the Haskell world.
These get used a fair bit in real in
real production code.
um... a less-known idiom is that you can
compose Traversable functors the same way
How many people here are familiar with
Data.Traversable? So I have some idea.
Ok.. How many are familiar with, like, "mapM"?
"traverse" is like a generalized "mapM".
uh... "Applicative" is slightly weaker than "Monad".
Okay? With an "Applicative" you don't get..
er you only get that there is a combinator "ap"
or "liftA2" or whatever that you can use
that instead of "bind".
So you don't have all the power to
choose the next calculation based on
what value you've gotten out before,
but you can still
stitch together "Applicative" results
Okay?
And "traverse" looks like this:
It says given a function from "a" to "b" that has
"Applicative" side-effects in "m",
I can take an "f a" and give you an "m (f b)"
and if this was "mapM", this would be
a "Monad" "m".
and if it's "mapM" out of "Control.Monad",
that'd probably have "[]" here.
So the "Traversable" class says "I don't care
what kind of Applicative you give me..
you give me an Applicative, and I will
walk through my "f" and find all the "a"s in it
turn them into "b"s and give you back "f b"
but if you look at the signature here
we can compose this! "traverse . traverse"
looks a lot like "traverse"
just in the same way that "fmap . fmap"
looked kind of like "fmap"
I just now have "f (g a)" and I'm not bolting
a "Compose" newtype in here to make this really painful
to work with
here with "traverse . traverse"
I'm now saying if you give me "f (g a)",
I'll go in there. I'll go into the "f"
I'll find all the "g a"s.
I'll go into the "g"s find all of the "a"s
Transform them into "b"s using your
Applicative side-effects
and I'll pull the Applicative side-effects
all the way out through the "f".
And similarly: "traverse . traverse . traverse"
So i can keep going deeper and deeper
you can actually mix and match these
"traverse . fmap . ...", but
they start doing strange things.
You have to be careful.
And that actually leads us to why we
want to do something slightly different
So I want a version of "fmap" that
I can compose with "traverse" in the same way
So I could say I can go into a "Functor"
where I only have a "Functor" for it, but
I have a "Traversable" for this other
other outer container.
So if we look at the definition for the
class of "Traversable"
"Traversable"s have two super classes.
We're gonna gloss over one for
about ten minutes until I need it
But every "Traversable" is a "Functor"
because given the definition of "traverse"
i can choose an appropriate "Applicative"
to be able to derive the definition
of "fmap". i could use the "Identity"
monad, or the "Identity" "Applicative"
and then this becomes "a -> Identity b"
abated
and "f a -> Identity (f b)" and I can
just put on or off the newtype wrapper.
and I can derivate "fmap" from "traverse".
Okay? So that motivates the superclass
of "Functor" for "Traversable".
And um...
there is an "fmapDefault" that is provided
for you in "Data.Traversable".
which is
a valid definition of "fmap".
So if you've written a "Traversable" instance for a type
you could just use "fmap = fmapDefault" and
you'll get the uh... the "Functor"
for it. It will define it for you.
You won't have to walk through your whole
your syntax tree a second time doing
the same thing just without the
"Applicative" side-effects
But let's take that guy apart.
The source code for "fmapDefault"
says
I'm going to "traverse"
I'm going to take the function that you gave me
from "a -> b" and I'm going to
bolt an "Identity" in and I'm going to give you
an (a -> Identity b) so not that is suitable so that
I can pass it to "traverse".
um...
Then this will be.. this will take in my "f a"s
and this is going give me back an "Identity (f b)"
So I'll "runIdentity" to rip the "Identity" of and
I'll have an "f b".
This build "fmap" out of "traverse".
just using "Identity" out of like "Data.Functor.Identity"
This is in "transformers".
and these are the operations that
you define for an "Applicative".
"pure" is like "return" and this
is a weaker thing than "bind"
So, remember we had
"fmap . fmap . fmap" up there
uh...
uh... we can define
we could take the definition of "fmapDefault"
and we if we ripped out "traverse" here..
If we didn't make this use the "Traversable" class..
If we passed this in as an argument..
What Traversal I want to use
I could make a function that looks a lot like "fmapDefault".
We'll call it "over" -- I have "under" and
some other ones that are related as well.
and then if we look at the definition of
"over traverse f"
this is going to turn into
"runIdentity . traverse (Identity . f)"
but we know this is just the definition
of "fmapDefault"
and "fmapDefault" is a valid definition of "fmap"
so "over traverse"
is effectively going to the same amount
of work as "fmap"
and if we give this thing a signature
uh... we're going to be able to go from
"(a -> Identity b) -> s -> Identity t"
to a function from "(a -> b)" to "(s -> t)".
This is a semantic editor combinator.
This is something I don't know.
this could be true
this could be
um...
the signature of "traverse".
[Audience: are those parentheses unbalanced?]
What's that?
you can be put parens around this chunk..
Oh! I missed a paren over here.
Yes, I screwed up
This should have a parenthesis. Here.
So
we'll call this type here, a "Setter" for right now.
And a setter lets me just update.
I can't..
uh...
I can't do certain other things to it yet.
But a "Setter" can be used to generalize
this "fmap . fmap . fmap" chain
just like semantic editor combinators did originally.
So let's make up something to build a "Setter".
We'll make a function named "mapped",
because "fmap" wasn't a "Setter".
It was a semantic editor combinator.
Right? it had the..
it was the..
"(a -> b) -> (f a -> f b)"
but it didn't have a um..
"Identity" mucking things up.
"mapped" basically just bolts the "Identity" in.
and then if we lookat "over mapped f"
this is "runIdentity . mapped (Identity . f)"
but we can expand the definition of "mapped"
so this becomes
"runIdentity . Identity . fmap (runIdentity . Identity . f)"
so we can collapse the "runIdentity . Identity"s and we just
get fmap.
so we can see that "over mapped" is "fmap"
and "over traverse" is "fmap".
So you can pass this thing "mapped", which would work
for any "Functor" or we can pass
would work for any bunker or we can pass
it "traverse"
or really anything that
I'll call a "Traversal" in a few minutes.
So we can we can just passed this
function anything liked "mapped".
or "mapped . mapped"
and it will just work
so any any "Setter" that i can construct
I can pass to "mapped"!
And "traverse" can be made to be a "Setter"
by just picking the "Functor", because
we're allowed to pick any "Functor" we want..
er.. any "Applicative" we want.
We'll just pick the "Applicative" to be "Identity".
Right? The type system will do that for us when
we go to pass it in to something that expected
to pass it into something that expects a Setter.
So that gave us
the ability to
walk into something
so
but um...
lets maybe use that
himself, so "over mapped" add one to every element in this list.
that once you have really been the
slowest
ignore the uh... laundry list of the modules loaded there..
Well maybe I want to say "over (mapped . mapped)"..
but notice that this -- unlike the lens
library that we described at the
beginning of this -- that we can actually
change types here.
So my lenses can actually go in many structures deep
change out the types and pull them back out. er..
I'm not actually using mapped as a lens, this is a "Setter"
still.
but setters can still be used to change types.
so i said.. everywhere inside this thing
where i'm going two levels deep
you know mapping through structures
go through and compute the length of
each of those strings
I just wanted to motivate this
with a little bit of an example.
Because, we've been talking a lot of theory for a while here.
So we can make lots of these things..
like if i had "Data.Text".
"Data.Text" is now what you'd traditionally think of
as a 'Functor".
It is not a container.
in the classic sense that it's
polymorphic and what what it can hold
It can only hold characters.
but we can make a "Setter"
for the characters in a "String"
er.. in "Data.Text"
um.. so you say
if we unpack this thing, now we've got a string..
let's go map over the string
and then pack it back up
uh... and this
matches our definition for a Setter
and "over chars" will
go in and do the right thing.
And we can go into lists of characters
or
any "Traversable" container holding other
characters
er.. holding onto
"Text" fragments.
And we can map over each
of the characters inside of
my containers full of containers.
By the way? How readable is this?
I should have asked that,
probably a long time ago.
This is a lot of small text. I apologize.
So derived from the "Functor" laws
..I think i can zoom..
..Control-zoom.. yay!..
so if we look at the "Functor" laws
that "fmap id = id".
and "fmap f . fmap g = fmap (f . g)"
um...
in in the in the case of "Functor" you
can actually derive the second law from the first
and parametricity.
uh... in the case of "Setters" you can't.
You.. you don't get this one for free, unfortunately.
uh...
we can make analogous laws for setters that we would
like to have hold.
they say that if you go "over" a setter with "id"
it should be the identity.
and if you go over it with "f" and over it with "g"
it's the same as going over it with the composition.
but we can make setters that don't look anything like
uh...
a valid "Functor".
like here I'm going to walk over both halves of a pair.
Here you can give me a pair where the the two sides match in type and
I'll give you a new pair were the sides match in type as long as you
give me a function from "a" to "b".
and I have to sprinkle the "Applicative" sugar through that
uh... or i can walk over the first element of this, so
given a pair of an "a" and a "c"
uh... if you want a "b" and a "c",
give me a function from "a" to "b".
and i'll give you
a function from "(a,c)" to "(b,c)".
and we can actually see that in use over
here
so if I want to go in here..
and say..
sorry for my colorful example..
there. um...
so now we're going into a list
and then into the pairs inside that list
where the types of the
two halves of the pair have to match originally
and then they'll match in the output.
and here I'm passing in a function from "String -> Int"
and i'm getting out
a list of pairs of ints.
and we can of course do this in a smaller setting as well.
So there are lots of combinators for working with setters.
I'm just throwing them up here
sort of like a scare slide I admit.
The substance of it is is that
you can construct a "Setter" from a
semantic editor combinator or from a functor.
uh... you can..
You can actually use "traverse" directly as a "Setter".
We saw that early on.
uh... there's lots of combinators for working with them:
"over" ..
There is an infix version of "over" that is convenient
in a lot of code.
um...
and then if you're used to just doing
things like "+=", and "*=" and
those kinds of things inside of imperative code..
if you are working in a state monad..
and your state
is something that you have a lens into
you can do (+=) to modify part of that state
That will modify *all* the targets for
the setter inside of the inside of your state.
So is actually more powerful than the
(+=) notion that you are used to in imperative code,
because it can hit multiple targets.
um...
This (%=) is something where
if you think about it as "mod" like an imperative programmer.
This is mod-equals, right? Thats why..
it's a modifying it with a function
um...
it's.. it was named for a pun
it at least gave me some mnemonic for what
what the modify thing should be.
um...
and we can we can "set" or directly just
change the value to its new target
This is like passing it "const b"
for this function instead of
passing it an arbitrary function.
there's lots of thing to do with it
Setters I think make a nice entry point
to the library because they hint
at the structure that we want
We got them directly by looking at
the definition of "fmapDefault" that was already
there -- that was defined for us inside of
"Data.Traversable"
um...
We stole the laws wholesale from "Functor".
We didn't have to make up laws for setters.
They were already given to us.
by the sort of
canonical choice of what a Setter should look like,
which is Functor.
So lets do Traversals.
So we saw that we could pass "traverse" as
a "Setter".
What if we
tried to generalize _this_ pattern
instead of just generalizing "fmap . fmap . fmap .."
Lets do "traverse" and "traverse . traverse".
Because, remember, "over traverse f" gave us "fmap f".
We might we might be able to find "mapM" in terms of traverse.
Actually, mapM is defined in terms of "traverse"
inside "Data.Traversable".
but for the default definition of "mapM"
they use this "WrapMonad" and "unwrapMonad"
This is a newtype. They are
the putting on and taking it off.
Here this guy says, given a Monad for "m"
I'll give you an "Applicative" for "WrapMonad m"
okay and since i've got an "Applicative" I
can go through "traverse" and now that I've gone through "traverse"
I can pull the "WrappedMonad" off and I'll have done the work.
Using that same pattern of just pulling
um...
the "traverse" out of this definition and
replacing it with an argument
we can get a similar definition for "mapM"
that takes the "Traversal".
and so the says if you give me an "s"
and any monadic function from "a -> m b"
i'll give you an "m t".
given a "Traversal"
the goes from "s" to "t" and given
function from "a" to "m b" for any
monadic or applicative side effect you want.
so "mapMOf" could be defined
in terms of
our "Traversal", just by
pulling traverse out of the function
and so now "over traverse f" gave us "fmap f"
but "mapMOf traverse"
give us "unwrapMonad . traverse (WrapMonad . f)"
which is exactly
the definition of "mapM" above.
So we can see that we've generalized the existing notion of "mapM"
by just pulling out the "Traversable".
and there are laws that we already know for "Data.Travesable"
The "Traversable" laws are just these:
"traverse pure = pure" and
"Compose . fmap (traverse f) . traverse g = traverse (Compose f . g)"
Now, in the end of the slides I have some
references, Jeremy Gibbons wrote
a very wonderful paper on
"The Essence of the Iterator Pattern"
In the process of working on this
with Russell O'Connor
He was able to prove that these
are all of the laws that you need!
There were a couple side conditions
that were floating around in
"The Essence of the Iterator Pattern"
Those turned out to all be consequences
of those laws.
There's a paper he's been putting together
that actually goes through with the formal
proof of this in Coq showing that all
traversals are finitary containers.
um...
So this spun off a little bit of research!
But the laws for a "Traversal" are just these. Just
rip out "traverse" and replace it with "l".
so a valid "Traversal" "l"
"l pure" should be "pure"
uh...
and if pure was Identity you could see
how this gives the Functor law.
and "Compose . fmap (l f) . " etcetera
That one is a little bit ugly, its inside
Jeremy Gibbons' paper
uh.. if you want more motivation.
But really what this guy is saying is
that your traversal doesn't change the
number of targets for the next traversal.
so if you apply a traversal,
and you traversed seven elements
the next traversal
if you were to apply the same traversal
would have to see seven elements again
That's a good litmus test of
whether or not you have a legal traversal
uh...
So we've got lots of traversals. Um..
"traverse" is a "Traversal"!
(let's see if i pan this correctly)
uh... "both", which we saw earlier
we wrote both as a "Setter" originally, all right?
but we were just using arbitrary "Applicative",
so both can be a traversal.
We can traverse the "Left" half of an "Either".
instead of having to "traverse" the "Right".
Well we don't even have the instance of "Traversable"
for "Either", so..
oops. I think I was supposed to write that.
(I should do that)
But in the meantime you can use a traversal!
uh...
actually these are called "_left" and
"_right" and they are actually
more general than this
in the actual lens library
but then we can come down here and say
"over _left (+1) (Left 3)"
but if I gave that guy "Right 3" it would
just leave it alone
If I gave it (Right "hello") it wouldn't
care about the type not matching, yeah.
It is only looking for the type on the "Left".
uh...
and if we compose these things it'll
walk into the left half of an "Either"
there and then into both.
also notice something here, though.
the order of composition here is
I'm going into this structure
and then into this one!
The order reads left to right and not right to left.
and that will be really useful in a minute
because of the ordinary an
imperative programmer would kind of expect
field acccessors to go, you know?
I'm accessing "foo.bar.baz.quux" and adding ten.
So,
If i said
uh... (&) here is just "flip ($)".
It makes for cute syntax. [laughter]
I could've written this thing with..
Right?
And "_2" is a very interestingly named
operator for basically "snd" as a lens.
uh... we have them up to "_9". They are
actually polymorphic you can work with them
on
arbitrarily large tuples (up to 9)
um...
they just do the right thing
[.. A long, mostly inaudible question from
Jay Sulzberger about the inability of Haskell
to express naturals at the type level..]
We do have these around now, but..
but it but it's very hard to correlate
those two
it is very hard to program
polymorphically over arbitrary sized tuples.
We don't have a k-tuple, where the kth tuple is
indexed by n.
[Jay: That'll be in the next version]
[laughter]
Maybe.
Well, we'll have type level naturals anyways.
So let's let's us go through and edit part of the structure.
So,
The nice thing about building up..
in this order
is that if i start here
i can
start with say a blank record
and now it looks like build up a record
by setting this field equal to this value
and this field equal to that value
Right? you can actually read it off
um...
and that this works for arbitrary
setters or traversals or
lenses as we'll see. heh..
they'll all just.. they'll all just work
uh... One a main goals of the
lens library has been to make it so that
whenever you reach for any combinator
and almost any type that you think it
could work with
it should "do it" and it should do the right thing.
uh...
and it it worked out
pleasantly by accident,
but it worked out really well!
uh... so we've been trying to
maintain that property
so..
if we go "over (traverseLeft.both)" ..
we'll be able to walk into
all of that.
So, those are Traversals.
There is a whole host of combinators for working with Traversals.
In "Data.Traversable" there is a whole bunch of combinators
for working with any Traversable container.
If you take any of the combinators that are in there
and bolt "Of" on the end of the name of it
it
you can pass it a
Traversal directly and it will work
with any traversal you've written.
uh... and so that means that i wrote a
_traversal_ now, for traversing
the characters in Data.Text..
If you look in the API for Data.Text,
it duplicates almost the entire Prelude
for everything that deals with a list!
But most of those combinators are things you
could derive from Traversable
if it was an actual "Traversable" instance.
and so what this lets me do a shrink the API
for working with Text down to more or
less two functions..
and a bunch of combinators that work
with everything.
So if you are looking for the
selling point of this, its that
APIs like Data.Text are wonderful.
They are really high-performance.
They work really well.
But they don't feel very Haskelly.
You have to import a module..
but you have to import it qualified
because all the names collide with
everything else from the Prelude.
With this, the API for working with Data.Text is
compatible with the API for working with everything else.
You don't have to import anything
qualified in order to work with these
text fragments.
um... and it really cleans up
the code that results.
I an actually show that off.
load Data.Text
and load..
a little helper library
and say if i had
hello, packed
I'm going to use syntax I haven't introduced yet. I apologize.
If I look at that.
this is Text.
I'm saying use
something to read out
from a list, so that gave me Text.
and i could go through and say well if
any of..
the text characters
are equal to 'c' in
[Audience member: can you zoom in?]
I totally can..
Well, that made it worse
eh...
that's about as good as I can go. That work?
so "anyOf text (=='c')"
and "hello", hrmm. that was a little too small.
uh...
I lost myself.
I can at least put it on the screen now.
and:
anyOf text (=='c') ("chello"^.packed)
and this works
in "both.text"
if i had..
if I worked with "chello world"
we can walk into
characters that are inside of
a pair of Text fragments
and "anyOf"..
"any" is a combinator in "Data.Foldable"
uh... I'm jumping all over the place.
[Audience member: Does this work with fusion in Data.Text?]
Uh... no
You get a beautiful API.. and you lose all your fusion! [laughter]
That is the price. um..
Data.Text is very very performance
conscious and if you really want
maintain that performance consciousness
you probably have to use
qualified imports, but if you just wanted to
munge some Text around..
and you already have the rest of this
stuff open
it can in practice be quite useful.
so if I zoom back out..
"anyOf" actually doesn't need "Traversable"
in needs
"Foldable"
When.. when I introduced Traversable
I glossed over one of its ancestors.
and that is that
Foldable bassically provides you with
[END OF CAPTIONING]
if you could you pick nothing away also
involve all
they give you to rest
as a function visited seznam if you give
me an acrobat give you a list of it
ad and wanted a company merritt says do
you give me any model i'd
to any of the city where you have a
socially law and you have a unit for it
and
papon to propose to market to know that
my life
popping up all day
an up or if there's a modeling for less
because the idealist and plus plus
so we can just use told not to get out
bullets
soviet nuclear you'd never simple dot
bored
i think it is there's two s
and you'll fill your burger because no
so now when we did
traversed at riverside riverside apm
apple apple apple apple apple dot i dot
go dot
the
we do the same thing pullback
so-called not
unfold not dump all mapinfo mapinfo
mapinfo map
all these guys were acceptance i don't
miss this side of the people in that it
is
each of them
says that they have the same pattern
that we have heard rumors
and
jurors will didn't just give us
acceptable to give us bought map apple
they gave us inversion up all about for
free
if you're not interested in playing
i can give you
ballmer
and here's where we need a generality
traverses walk-ins
such reversible
doesn't need a mona it needs it looked
like it
breaking work within the party
remember quit
something that i can't make a monocle
constant constant provided by control of
it
and and basically says if you give me an
at the old constand a
doesn't have any agent
right just absent
but as the powdered really easily
i don't care about the age argument i
could just throw it away and and you
know i can't i can't make and replica
constants are dropping a bit of economic
blueprint
quite the only thing that i'd kept me up
i got my emp no joint it was in my
thoughts
bob and i can make an instance of
applicable for this uh... just by saying
well when i got a couple obscure value
like return after the volcano of a were
as a good day to you
const ami
twenty to come up with an m_r_i_ nowhere
so i can use an update from my
my modeling
so this is an active can construct a
value
i don't care what
value you gave me so i don't have a
place but the air
and to throw it away
and you have to
const about his new york optimum
together that's with that
uh... underscoring the used
mccann
that it'll elliott's pointed uh...
through that one of these days
so i'm going to i'm going to
uh... use the op-art goggle
the binary operation of the remark
to stick stitched together by
women all of us
uh... so given a model i'd for amb
const of m
is afflicted
at the pump your regardless and this
will be important later so i'm going to
make that distinction
constand is always a popular
and if you have a monogram it becomes a
wicked
we need a moderate because we don't have
any other way to magic up
uh... of value part when we don't use it
there were no one got out of it i think
that we don't have a awaits the together
and beat
a socially of our of our moderate enough
to get his wish to be one of the
equipment
now we can look at what we can look at
fault not the fault the ball not
appalled
calico use right at any other here
just say uh...
read that you did they do and identity
of bringing in a died in a t_v_ by this
wrapping up my enemy
bring to the same thing the rabbit
getting const
and win again consummate aside so this
is
he's the actor
sued basically saying that i really
don't care what we should be made
because the act
are here i don't care what the choice of
b you make because i'm just going to
const
and b
down and the unending
all napa all
is defined in terms of traverse
we've kind of established a pattern for
what we do grip on tunes that look like
that though
um...
so
and you're right lou
stupidly dance again
so taken bold not default we debate
apart
we can pull traverse out of there
replace it with
something local health for the past it
in his argument
will put colon cancer dac i was hoping
to get your is
and it will give us a signature that
works
right uh... i didn't have to make
anything out
beautiful view it should be
we can make op
kelly when we did
uh...
when we work with setters we we don't
math so that over maps turned into act
up
i want some things that i can pass it so
that when pulled up others applied to
say folded
this should be
would you give this issue resolved for
that matter
what are the same thing
which was there for the cost
might characterize
so pulled map of was kept constant
that alcohol so that
if i choose folded to be const
that bold map i'll get on startup
then paul bappa folded
turns in to get cast of const
appalled that will get past that kant
and we can destroy these two
defcon stuck aunts
has become sport bab
we've gone through the relation we've
proven that this is
you know sort of the
deeper
folders at work
and given any folder
weekend begin to find the stamina vocal
view
and bureau says
i'm just gonna pass
const
and you can now get cut
going back to abusing things averages
jet
uh...
why do you want out of
hello
uh... yes older not
uh... yeah
cook
review folded
will say if you give me any foldable
half
and a model a big
uh... and i'm gonna give you another
horrible projector
uh... i'll give you a day
a pontoon from
appleby two b
you're looking at
generalize to use that word of
uh... that the actual documentation for
this is really nice thing to do about
ten makes type signatures you can look
at the u_s_ having
think about it
um...
bone review bolded
uh... their inside of data that uh...
uh...
foldable invincible double
their their sport map there's all are
others walking generalization for the
common or video
and one of them is called for the masses
basically saying if you have all
a container full of my moral values
i'm going to
uh...
what u
like calculate a mno some basic level
like just the stitch decision together
with one of the notebook
the action has been a model
so we got a few folded
this is going to turn in to get concert
on support that
because icons
this is called navid which is
e ful
and we can make up this guy will call up
the odd couple there's going to say
that for any choice of m you pick any
this is missing a monitor
for all amb
such that there's a monogram
give me a a doubt const them of a i'll
give you a pampered asked the cost of
about
so thats
they nice way to work with
here so we can work with
uh... anything that we do have bid up
audible we can do with the pool
to like anne allen
some
product billable
fifty commenters however
um... they all general so some of both
will go through an adult
both on the toddler or some of traversed
upload will go through
some traversed will be there for
terrorist
in and out the values uh... all of the
both sides of the
workers' incentive
buzzword
what we want something that was
more powerful
than a traversed uh...
we look at the signature here
traverse all centerfold
we we're up we're up about
nation-building and a whole piles up on
this planet
um... brother diversion appalled map of
to list of says there's a great you give
me up
uh...
convert downward
i got underscore one which would walk
over the first applecare
i don't need it
all of the power of the traverse will
get
to result as that
you pick any applicable
and i have to be able to use fabio upon
the facts are
here i'm only using
here i don't care about them online
met met
you know i mean are you doing underusing
you are saying the beautiful before
but new mother cara bottom online
your al your your uh... your particular
pull
might care about them online
the sublet it might as well this code
without anything leaders on it i said do
you understand one out of ten
uh... out of a pair for the twenty will
just give me back ten
uh... without a model eight on the
continent
that will work
so i obviously missed something
so deadly fad
a couple of additional members this
hierarchy we can fill in the gap
so that we can make
the signatures purview
and the signature of to list um... you
know all the things that make sense
what we want your is elevens are lesser
said getting
would be
i'm gonna get out something i'll use
this particular model or this particular
confident that my
constructor it may not may not be
anomaly because i'd i'm nothing at work
training on items that he works for our
and i must say in a caused art
as to plans are
so i want some power from paul
again the ability to
um...
but with this in particular
and if we just wrote the signature of u
you would look like getting a out of
asking abt
survivors o
raspy eighty were saying they given upon
too from a to b i gave you
it
uh... nolte in beer completely
irrelevant
we don't care about them
was any of them so that we can actually
pathname
when things will get our and for the
summer
and
i'm gonna just past the sky const
susan allen to beat any const indeed
another's estimate as to constipated
it's like getting have that concept that
i could get the any
i packed in here so
gives me a lot
interview
didn't demand of my life
out of the elements of my
if you happen is that with the fall
will demand a model
because the says this work as long as
you you can become on a crab
but view itself doesn't demand a model
all mapa even doesn't banana market
right on doing a dime applying you're
probably going to vegas some value card
we'll call it um...
the convenient
but i'm i'm rapid advance
so i did was presenting his view as both
a function and
i'm getting the cars that i got
i'm getting
endeavour
it may or may not be a model
so i apply for map up to a fault
unlike the man
amato i don't know
but i fight together
journey
now
uh... i will not
so we get
is we can make
if centers
we have
getters are missing decker
that list
so we can do is we can make this notion
of a lands
the any traverse eliza valid getter and
i'm missing the point one three missing
jeter missing
um...
we read the definition of get extra tape
asking abt
yesterday
reports
results
even if a chilly conse parbe
i can give you an asteroids comets
so we can
the finest biology to v
were polled said
you can rely on the fact that i have a
model
alligator doesn't give you this
so you have your if this does work for
any
function who made a consular
which is just that there is a factor of
fun to be a bunch of eight r
idea punch mass start liking of nothing
about
if they can do anything about our i
can't put together in any meaningful way
so i had to do is
fine
the won the hearts out of here
structure that this represent
this is a fancy way to say that i have a
function for mass today
though i have
uh... governor skipper ornaments lights
right
so i gather
is unified request and i will give you a
better
which is that for all our
itic onstar
and we can build too
and this guy says if you have lunch from
este
and i thought you know they are with the
new right
i need a bunch rasool with me
let's
like flip-flop
antonyms
reads a
to his
i'm composers dupont jonsman ripped the
consul off of the cutback
no
okay
it's got a boring
and there will be the review to you
this is going to be just like they did
before
rupal plug in the definition of two
picasa contradict absecon stand out
let them get all
regan leh pungent smell smelly mud drop
bombs in the normal and arrival
ladies like white wine
and get something that's kinda like a
land title of his reversal kinda like a
full
but it's just a pontoon to get one
valley
and if you didn't demand it be a
monolith it just worked
growing about website
so now
a lens
is just
eight reversal
that is a ballot yet
so if they traverse a loved one targeted
side of the structure and they have to
cut in half a diverse one target
given there's no way to build
this ab
to give it back to you honored that you
use your function
from a double date
right i have no not knowing audit up
other than the fact that the bump in the
end of the bunker that battle
and of the laws on
on terms such that
really doesn't matter however over it if
i have to happen in about the second
time i can always attach that the other
so
what what what that means is that i have
to go into my house
find a day
somewhere i think that we can talk or
not you know
a quicker
by an egg in a few by
pat calling upon check-in appleby out of
it
and then full the rest of the crap that
was inside a bass
under the answer inside of the model
inside of that the parker
there's nothing else i can do
joel ends
now under this formulation is just
andy's reversal
that happens to be
abella gather
because the debtor just said that the
sweat that cost army nothing about this
but we knew that
are
was a functor no matter what choice of
our wicca
its not applicable must we all my life
but we only have about a reality of it
with your work with
and i went really faster that's a there
will be hopefully video not cook up a
bit nervous
uh...
or we can do it is now as we had view
and sat
uh... setlist like bright too
and view let us re renew our way back to
the anymore and i think i would never do
anything and public threw it out
we can now derived the definitions from
that's like
in terms of this much crazier looking
construction
work
uh... here
deal with picking declined to be
constand
and satisfy king it to be agony
british choosing two different bunkers
probably
there were a lot of attorney bob we
walked on giving them the item in here
and so using that that power
we can read the single target out
or we can set up
but interestingly if i pass this guy up
all
now
spontaneously this is going to start
demanding that this argument be among
if you don't owe money for the net
you the answer a fault who doesn't have
any weight a smash together
all of the different response
so view works for polled say works for
lenses that works for commercial
leverage over sold about fall
so it will just be wild card to the
commercial
uh... and what we can sort of a
subtyping relationship between all of
these different right there with
where
using them in different contacts cause
these commentators demand according to
the
when we did buell earlier we reviewed
underscore one out of
hello
underscore one
was owens
a length of the vote getter
by getter can reads exactly one target
doesn't men amano tell us when we got a
but i wanted you both have said that she
would have to do something to that it's
got a state that should be getting
anyone trying to rescue strengths
just any as the model a first reading
there
uh...
and if we really want we can get them
out separately conflicts converts a list
well if there is yours is gonna complain
that does not do this
there was nothing to have a
we can say jimmy's and some of us
if that's going to pick up my life is
good inject them into the some model
item n
steelworker
there yes and and and do that
that is the instance of my my purse
strings
just yes it was a by default
you couldn't you could make up as a
moderate for any
yes because they did you really want to
adam you are more quiet
you know you it does not mean you could
so wet when there's no one right before
we just don't people
usually then you have to pick up
anything
well you can make it you can use any
type reveron like
that i could use um...
view both of
uh... district is not something that
missile effect
that's on the pillow talk
hypocritical
um...
kal okay
so now
we were able to build with view and sat
we can construct a lens given a
and a setter
but now we've got these funny b_n_p_
backgrounder winner wage but we think
about why that changed
right because we're we're allowed to
change the type are targets right
so before we talk about when the the
very beginning we just said that
well if i if i start with a alum
passing it made out
ever got up
an awsome and you and i can go back in
again you are
here what i'm saying is maybe wanting to
pay for that part
or all of the targets
involved wondered is were the ones
if you change the type of that target
will be
the new technology
again then turned out that you get this
family structure where
you've got like the out her family and
in her family and they they both have
indexes and i
written up
blog post on the topic is that if we
want to do indeed
uh... but
the
structure here usually sit is
a good way to tell if you've got a bell
atlantic you could all if you can always
pick
testicle steven eight will be
if you can't than you
probably screwed up and you don't have a
look
well the government you know
is a good witness trucks
if i gotta go from este
and a piano that's totally
and it came to a couple of pieces can i
have a nice
i date my aspirate last day
by midday if you'd like what you may not
be used
niigata annapolis bees like that that
will be looking at the movies
thank you compete
that was in my computer
and the absolute pleasure
and smash together guarantees nyah nyah
forties
and i need
that's an extra bed
their stockbridge
so again a lens update the single target
and you can define a lens in terms of a
debtor
in practice i'd never bothered to do it
this way
because its
is here for me and practice just a
closer to about and a pair of a and b
should look like
where the now
reminders wicker shelf life
that's alliance
as soon as i have everything
uh... um
also know something here
i didn't have to import my library to
write back
there
brett so you can write lenses that are
compatible with the lens library
unifying commercials that are compatible
with the lens library
without dip
pending fumble and wiper
ratkai just used this guy could be a
staff map of the prelude i wouldn't have
been
orgasm using just the prelude you can
define the land
it is perfectly compatible with pollock
commons i give you a cooler
and one of the reasons that this is
important is
is that did you view
kab all kind of like an onion their
entire something where he like
packages come along and they may just
get calendar layers on the onion
uh... later packages
how do you have to provide all of the
stuff
per pack a dessert
deeper than them in in in uh... in the
west is really hard inverted dependency
in the fall world
uh...
and you can have cycles
so if i were to come along later in the
final library
i do have some great instances for
containers i'd better put them on my
library because there's no way i'm
getting containers depend on me
on the other hand with business
i could say i did try and convince your
honor degree somebody and other gotta go
alligator steam
to make a
islands to go to burst the offer
argument on the part of the
and
that might be an argument i could win
uh... and so this is this
uh... somebody made a joke that i've got
to the point where bob might well
aberrational point we don't have to
depend on them
anymore popularity of any of them uh...
not
um
i think is a really big selling point
for this kind of lands
if nothing else
uh... because it solves that twelve
which might lead to invite radio i
provide lens for
uh... you don't have to become a
dependency in his right about here
yeah
itself
so this this is by the critical
uh... and then the other thing is is
this just magically become the
commercial if i started to say
well and
walk this one too
objects o traverse als and pump and
lenders can both be provided by any
library
without leaving depending on
link line doesn't have a some are all
yet
if you can
breaker prep
yep so given
upare
apiece
and a bunch of repute up badly than ever
apparent
but now
because i have to be able to smash
together the answers
immediately
and that's the thing that will magically
make independent amato right when you go
to use
one of the old comic
so you can use this traverse or as a
whole
as it were sold
it just works
you use this lands
reminders were too
as a old garrett reversal all things are
good may just happen to be instantiation
to the fact that we can
so we can now make
missing the definition of that
uh...
so we want to go defying
elan's into a map
like innately might say won't give it a
key into them
i want to go get you the value at that
it like
that doesn't white
what about you mention what value liking
you
at the end with your father
so i can't do this
i try to write the paper
delicate reversal birth you know
and that you updated if it's already
present
but that's not letting you know
create akeel or
but what i can do
so we can say mapped out from us this
terrible amount
so this is at the site
uh... matthew to insert delete and do it
it builds up
annoys size balanced binary tree
performed really well
so we can read it up a lot
this is an ethical review
we do reiki is not present
in dozens of april levees that's getting
out and maybe
close to a permit
so i can read and write to it
but i can i can only read in right now
is akin to leap from the map using
eleven
and that's how i can meet the landforms
is that not only do i read
and right
i can delete because i can go from
given a key
i give you a lens that looks at the
value that he had to present
or gives you nothing of its not
and it will insert it when you put up a
bit suggest
and will be a lead if you put up with
them
now act is actually generalize that
worked with it option somewhat but
in fact conceptually you can think of
that as having the signature with a
maybe a again
although i pull the wool
we talked about
um...
there's a whole bunch of numbers you
carry dupre
opal hit up a little right
but a lot of them
uh... we did we get them all
uh... but this of
convention
um...
burning lens provide something like six
or seven hundred different names with
things
that um... i actually did a good word
search like frequency analysis against
package before
releasing the library the try minimize
their complex so that's why we do the of
convention in suffolk va
um we have lots of past tenses i take
names and places that nobody does feel
like we use joined in person
huh
sojourn so we we who eating
and sort of you know
so that's what's holding them pull their
guns without
past tenses so things things that get us
names that are declarative
but our relatively underutilized
portions of the namespace of the people
can import lands unqualified because
control dot length brief and all the
stuff
uh...
at that point
and i really didn't want people happy
import something qualified or explicitly
near everything they do so
because it's really hard to give a talk
if you have to name
every door detroit using your card
before you can use it
here
uh... it it's it's much nicer to having
large vocabulary that you could just
reach for
and and in many ways
the lead bribery of all about building
that vocabulary for working with bunkers
and pull the wool
and reversible and function that we
already know how to use right
uh... so all we did all i did was to
take the pieces that we already know
although we are not a reason about
those those poor things
and put them together in a form that
makes them more comfortable
and makes them more applicable to that i
can to say
just grab this coming around chocolate
to give them has limited portion of them
and i can apply for the entire gamut of
over possible
uh... and so
the problem is a really convenient if
you have a poll
or a traverse all metlife is probably
furor when a woman few you have like
maybe
they didn't give me an answer may be a
while
um... this
this guy will go do you know the per
capita gin
the request matured a lot
uh... care about dot
get you a list of all the answers
on so i can do you think your not which
is uh... arm
its view
weapon into court
so the
killed on the others for like setting
operations like
it's functional centers
that supply this operator
and carrot dot as you carrot something
usually
i'm reading from a
compared
so here i am reading from a pull
and giving you maybe
here i'm reading from a hold of giving
you all the others the dot that should
be indicative of that but that that's
the best that you know yeah
so we got your essay given one too
and i'd lost my ability that the gospel
meat-packing
browning
uh...
one too
lee for
traversing the me though
or both double right
and then let's say that we had
three
tell me whether or not
and so most of the things you can do it
then the whole blvd recollection all the
things you can do to a beloved and in
doing a lot of things a build-up
the structure actually got the most
loving that you can use to build a
political action if the user deriva four
parents who writes departments like this
again urgent order
uh...
together just like functions
this is what you are supposed to drink
uh...
actually implement these are a little
bit of away like up until now i've been
saying that i got that
you just pick identity or you pick
uh...
const
uh... actually used
classwork
because if i don't get by user id by
actually just pet
conficker identity
and i know that i want to go green from
center
or write you a debtor
i would get a terrible looking
unification earth it would be like
srinu
okay but instead i quickens our class
constraint on it it will unify and then
it will look for instance that isn't
there
and i want to say no instance perak
others saleable music uh... access or no
inference of double nuclear
and now looks much nicer in some adopted
him getting into it what they did wrong
uh... so i actually can't match
that const construction by making a
class were things that are double
maganda setting for separate appleby
and why is that not about
wrapping up half people's court
so this this can't happen any minute
because
you know in order to satisfy that law
use the functions uh... map of it
uh... and so once i get done with that
now debtors not quite
uh... way that we go
reversible
art reversible and left
record reversal in lands
used functor looking at here using
double
and then
so it's an obsessive opinion of going
out to put it
polling often bring back on a new
contract or understand course
turnover may internet would be visit
yeah i know that that big a role
and getting
can still pick it to be accessories as a
friend inundated constantly
the standard
lenders
agis anything above the gutter of
commercial
uh... we had a whole piled commenters
really is um...
so today shouldn't you
um...
updating
the target
i can read the answer that i wrote
at the same because
uh... if they are beginning to go are
updated by
cutbacks variable count and that
happened over here
uh...
so i quit yes you can go through and to
find something like
i know left freshen equals
uh...
normal marxism
structured the
back cat
social say in any money at stake
that have caused the cut
uh... that has an america it
by ken
bump the car by one
and read the new value
online
are you would be identity lanphear
pledged by the way is just the identity
function
seven composing these things all im but
i haven't really talked about why they
compose right lol
if we look at this this is a function
from
in appleby too
estaba meat
and when i compose them i'm compiling
those functions the outer rappers
timeline from ada theater
as a victim here that goes well
uh... xd af of why eight af of b so i
compose those night open ac staff of y
de step
composing these larger box that's why i
can use dot mcgrew
you can actually build these things
using a rupture there if you really want
to
you know that arabs
just passport
uh...
everything composers backwards because
we're
if you look at this is a kind of sepia
so
we've got lots of things we know lenses
built you know i gather
built up just a c_b_s_ function
put into effect on that uh...
now let's do something fun
um... yeah
so up until now
we men just kind of manipulating happier
uh... there is a hack that i came up
with
fallible four years ago that are used to
know
a little play
overloading function application
everybody says you can't do this let
them and not everybody but a lot of
people so you can do this
uh... but again
right you know what to make
uh... datatype where you define how it
applies to values
but what we can do as we can make a
class such that are datatype is an
instance of the class
and
a function isn't it for the class and
then we can get overloaded function
application
and what i want to score
is i just want to be able to find a
function which i can run backwards
okay and i'm gonna turn it into a lot
berlet's
residents like
in small steps
and this is the slides hit the slight
here is a bit of a lot to learn how we
have to do it will end early mornings
this is the way we did up until three
points
electric one seven stretched
but um... i think this is about her
vision than that
but but the district would work
in the wild desperately
so what's are you wanted to make
isomorphism
specialize market with a bunch of that
you can apply like any other function an
asshole
but you could also use from
but right around
united workers on the other direction so
you can you could've life but then from
that from would be it
so i did was arrested
i'm a disc last night for want of a
better day might i called if by some
arctic
it's something that i can construct a
black market
survive if i have
a function from eight a b_
and a function from being a pain felt
that there could be emerges uh... uh...
they're usually work with
i can give your pay
personal
and i can make
functions themselves
the essence of isomorphic
just by lorraine this thing
i can construct a function
repeatedly in the park may be able to
that ripple
and i can make a good night
isomorphism
which actually captured both
and this would also be a perfectly valid
instance of isomorphic when they got
marbled with instructor look after the
eighty will capture the beauty of it
values both sides of the first time
delivery
bringing a category-four isomorphism
so we can compose isomorphism
so you have two important role i
category
to get its version of dot ended
inordinately composi
if you didn't
there's going to come down to functions
when you put them
actually perfectly good
so now
we'd say
you know it is nice work even if you
have any questions if you have
the the the the
nationally on the way along with that
uh... we didn't have much more press
more for them
millions though that they don't give up
a doing time being
is anything alleged market
that day
from katie from katie
so this can be checked this can choose
this day to be a poncho if you had any
contact would have to be a fun trip
higgins used in the eyes of our ability
to you that i think like from
or it has to be a nice marcus
so if i need access to both sides of the
pontiff i can turn this time around
and give you a new
so now would best i could say
you know um...
isomorphic
plus one and subtract one
didn't mean that function apt
and i can apply after five intuitively
six like it's a from half
six would be fine
uh... and with the composition works
so this gives us
overload isomorphism so work is
functions
but i want them as lenses write one of
the ways that we don't like that a lot
of other one library
louis what happened to me by so we just
give the isomorphism lightweight
kinda forget the fact that we
constructed out a whole clocked the
other way
you just get will use this is the center
and we just ignoring me
david were packed
but i want to have that that that full
power ternal ends around depict is it
means to an isomorphism i wonder when it
backward
so it like i did
inc here with the plus one of the crack
with them
so
let's make
i think so
kinda like london commercial
boring to do there's a run-up etc
came here the outer function that the
budget we're between a double b_ enough
seventy
nikkei
work his finances of isomorphic
and so now i can give you a punch enough
of me
that at seven p
or i can give you
past apathy made up a bit
i can pivot around that central error
okay this is the old way
the signature
but there's at least get you intuition
uh... and so this used to require us to
provide us all four function the new
version actually let slice of the both
of these
in order
wife
um...
but
all we're going to do is say you give me
that you two sets of mutually inverse
functions and i can give you
isomorphism family that works helical
and family
and then we go through and say
we make an isomorphism between spring
apcst
so that
taxed
or the senate
will this will take
street attacks by packing uh... opted
out of it uh...
will take
texas land mine back again
call it an isomorphism
ignoring illegal characters but without
that
because before pope
and then we can define our text reversal
earlier on
just from packed
the payments
by some of them
write backwards
an introvert combat
now i can post a nice o
with a drummer soul
and i got back to russel
because what happened was
when i do want to do this composition
this
forced me outside to be an actual punch
in a row
so there's activity on general which is
a balance is awesome arctic
uh... your return
packed around three years that at
isomorphism
but katie
dat chose pay to be a culture
and which option
and so this is where the cello world a
couple actually disposed
in practice we use
of what we're going to the pressure of
that lets us de l'alma minimalist
and there's actually
face similar construction for these
things we called prism set up a
mechanism to go to prison for that
presenter what happens if you'd like to
take a categorical warble lands
so they might have what you access one
field
about product like thing
or part of a product
and a
uh... prism but you access one
constructor out of a song
and so like left and right are excellent
president but not commercial both the
left mike kinsley
uh...
that's the bulk of the top
about is what i'd like
show like a deep dive in a couple of
quick things
think i'm done
i'm a democrat
okay that's about her
so
there's a how many of the view of using
a player ever to be in a place
seeing a play a library for doing it our
programming at school with written by
dale mitchell
armpits it should really nice it
performs really well it's fast
uh...
i embedded a copy of your plate inside
of less which seems kind of redundant
but what i did was iri defined the
interplay commentator so that they are
ballot reversals
are rather so the commentators can take
any traversal
and so that and that you know
play-by-play are actually commercials
i was actually saw the number probably
in a playpen then
as a side of the coming up
uh... dude
tender
so we can as you can define a class with
us at the say
played it as a class that knows how that
is a traverse alot of thinking about a
minute
it's like go find all of the sub trees
of my children that you have a syntax
tree go find me all the childhood one
level down you gave me a descendant
targets of extreme of the same time
provided some expression shin
them say by the balkans in order
it uses one of these guys that you
cannot do that
that builder complicate leaving all why
the complex tall also nearby brings a
bottle
uh...
in heels library he go thirty buildup by
data structure
uh... kinda mimic the shape of the
intermediate structure
and i don't have to adjust captured in
the environment and sizes are not
building up and hearing something down i
save all that time and that's world
speed
uh...
but you can make explicit in slow plated
and then unlike like his coming would
like rewrite which would take
parkinson's and in a play
because this his classname
um...
we just have rewrite uh...
which grammar right on
this case the center
most and take a traverse all
uh... ignore those scary looking
signatures that we really can't there's
no model
uh...
but
the
these governors are actually really nice
in that
organism
critical years things like uh...
using these purging our programming
being used by quick to say
don't look in
this word go look for hello world
uh...
there
strings
in here
and go for it all
uh... post-riot
that uh... data lengths
his prolific list of the
and define all the strengths rather than
all the events
and so that went into
returnable didn't like that
use mac we're going to find all the
string anywhere inside a researcher as
long as it is searcher keep it that was
it is the data
and the thing that i was looking forward
uh... but i can also update from
yeah because as a traverse ult
yet
so take that thing
and sets
fell by play
to modify everything
uh... converted all about the case
bosnian too
the
uh...
or my map m of underscore which will go
through an action
on bike way
puts your line
renew our lease things all of our dinner
current reversals just work
uh... and were able used by put his head
of a magic commercial it'll just be
whatever commercial we kinda want
uh... savior chile's you to write
controversial
it's there
socheata play it
no
in lens form
army combo it come to a lot of
commenters that were in the original
unified or really really handy
for rewriting contract reason what not
like i rewrite up will say
do you mean
by saturday goes that knows how to get a
delays and giving off onto my computer
mediated
that like is a real early michael
applied maybe it goes realtor needed
literals and turns them into literal
that is the negative value
insiders and a tree
soviet negative wit ok alternative
live
the negative right
um...
and we'll do is we'll plan it in a
bottom-up matter it'll work
they'll go into the eighties
the the descendants of a
of your your your problem with russian
look through some of her infant son
which was lapd you're going down
apply the the subject of the rewrite
roulette believes
until it doesn't apply anymore and then
walk into a tree
does one commentator and it works
um... bird doing hierarchical rewrites
not complex of
holes are both find all the one whole
contacts as a complex problem
that's a start on that
from the beginning of the talk
um...
all these nominees were derived from
they all work directly in an age
reversal
um...
it's a ticket is an incredibly powerful
efficient library and then there's one
other
kind of like the diving capital to do it
but we don't like
uh...
and that is different
so one of the questions i could ask a
lot are
what is the connection between zippers
and lenses
uh... and historically there really
hasn't meant a lot of but now there is
from
so zipper provides
are pretty nice if you know
so leaders and its allies tipper into
something let's atlas oracle were little
what is the type of us
so this is a separate uh... and for the
wamu view these things they look like my
country
um...
so we're starting at the top
and we're looking at him
and go down in up
no
uh... you were people we're conflicting
with new people
and so now i'm for joe if you see the
senate but
a new premises are messed with it if you
would like a bread from calicut you're
going to our website
there's a saying returning at the top
into a pair of strengths or down in one
st word word word outlook express
full and now we're looking at a single
character
and i want you to change
the focused element
and
i want you to move all the way to the
right
and change the focused on that uh... why
whatever type of progress with
show you the the answer to that
there
we walked down
into the first half of her
we walked down into the last year
scrub within like basically make such a
level where we can move left word in
rightward within the level so we take a
commercial
we can move left and right within the
traverse off
uh... so like left and right inside of a
zipper traditionally something where you
hafta make up a notion about the right
to make sense for your syntax rearward
and you had that figure out a class or
something browser coble workers like
that
now
you give me a terrific
zipper
doesn't have any constraints on that
i'd walk in anything
um...
music brenda one
whatsoever yeah
on those tenets
and give me are when we have to come in
to replace
that's ones
and traversed
the and
from within
that's about
and set the focus equal to
mannerism
so i went into individual bets a manager
starting at last
uh... releasing every at bat
i can't move left and right through the
bats setting them
pop back out of it
images use of the fact that i can tours
individual bets is out of in america
uh...
any data type that you want as long as
you can build some kind of windsor
traverse a lender that you can use the
zippers become abundantly
and then
pop and downed power plug breadcrumb
trail
proper portion of our country up
so given a lens it'll go down
argument reversal
that could welcomed there might not be a
personal note for the purpose of the
millions
so with investigative have maybe
you succeeded in doing
latin right actually became leftward
rightward
use geyser lawson record as well
the upcoming expert on
injure which let you tiger jerk the
zipper lock correct
of acute argument erection it will go
and gently snobby and if you jerk ipl
it will bail not coca
so the triangle reviewed toddler up in
your article at most element that will
it will
stay where you are if you'd rather go up
it'll just
um... it so it's
ability
but companies but the names were not
taken i checked
picture
nobody wanted to use those names returns
uh... dot
one opposites library at churches like
appeared riveted
uh...
no acc
and um...
so that that's basically what i got
receptors uh... they're actually happens
to be a lot more in the library um...
we've got a there's still a few if
you're interested in more uh... there's
a hassle and channel on fri node is
about forty five of us lurking in the
channel at all times that's right
answering one question for work in the
library
a lot of about them
i think we have separate matters in the
library now helmets
making very alarming progress running
version three point seven
uh... my certify months ago
uh... yeah
sorry for the whoever breaking a p_i_
but um... it's better that it is about a
live report
uh...
the um...
so the community has been pretty good
there's arm
there's a number of resources out there
for learning more about lenses um...
so first of all there is v
uh... lens back it up dot com we'll give
you a very
uh...
nothing on my screen website uh...
gives you you know um...
more about them in the tutorial in stop
and so there's a longer tutorial on how
to use lenses
various um the actual
did rob website for lands
uh... feel free to port library define
something wrong with the haddock to
recover
there's about
five hundred example back that's that
actually run every time we check in
uh... but but
keep the people's honest
about the documentation um...
beers spares a wiki
that has a lot of
the the stuff that i work through a
matter of asian
op bak about why we do a good thing
certain way it's etcetera
on there's a lot of resources out there
uh... try to get as much of it is
community in the morning enough it was
possible
'cause i'm only one person
and person reportedly warn you this
um...
and
are you
what people the understand lenses gotten
uh... not
i hope is that the useful
um...
that's all i've done
a
heart-rendering
for are cat
uh... might wrap up this whole
collection by various for instance uh...
if you look at like math intel
collections
they're not map rather they're they're
they're map
traverses pairs of key values where you
can't really reason about like the park
a reality of mac
so if you want to work with map you have
to map over mail and i converted to
malcolm
literally so in order to work with map
europe was always working like that
three bodies that have happened in it
uh...
and so uh... to me i'm one of the
strongest things that i get out of
are haskell is is permitted in the event
and lost
um...
when i when i look at the scala
collections library
there's very little that you can use out
of it parametric where there's very
little that you can go all this whole
because all containers i could be jesus
come later
i have used at hotmail ad-hoc
on a proper collection base a basis
presence here we have indexed reversals
for for maps
so there's a whole i didn't talk about
an expendable
uh... but like if you want to have
access to the keys inside of your mouth
while you walk over and i had something
very similar to that isomorphism ac
telecoms work within next reversals as
well so you have access to the keys and
putting up a huge reversal is that uh...
evolving you get index list of the cover
i find that particular approach to be
much more practically reasonable
van
the um... scholar collections approach
where
now i can mash i can map over the
contents but i can't reason about that
map out that map g equals map f tuje
because i might map in the meantime i
might smashed through two pulls together
that
now make my mouth
i know if you were omens of
controversial
um...
i likewise i'd like the ability to other
understand
demigod
in my experience writing a lot of celica
i have not had that
thinkin
he quickly
you know i really sitting in the library
cover souls or something but the nobody
wrote that
uh... no
at it really really is all about
politics i happen to be able to use the
lens commenters graph
um... and not lenses in themselves
because everybody hears the word lands
ago ally note that as i've looked at efi
labels that access url phalanx
um...
and really
i think after going through the content
of that doc al you've got a feeling that
this is not about that
it's
it's basically everything that i can
take out of the other hand for classes
that we already know how to use in-house
golan
and generalize applicable dot
though about the texans yes
arm
actually you know what they can do about
it
uh... i i i i have a yarnell diagram nah
we are so i think i added that in our
settlers have
accessories that
craft
no
so i was i actually a mouth agar i'm
describing the relationship between
those different classes right
so we can say that every traverse eliza
ballad bold
right beverage reversals of alexander
uh... every getter reaction of these
things ho actions were not according to
the chance to talk about
uh...
bring them down and i a gram and see
that everyone's canoes directly at the
debtor
everyone everyone's commute to work for
network in the above the fold
and as a way that i thought
sabri isomorphism is a valid lands and
develop prism
which is the period or just talk about
and by the visa valid commercial
offshore comment about the slides by
just by one of the
sneak that in there
i think that works
is as soon as i dropped up your
and ab
by gamblers
saudi arabia weak and pump tear so that
the bunker doesn't use the argument
you get get a ball which is that class
and it is briefly
right then and you get a better
did you have got to get a bulletin for
then you have the actual getter
class that we use
and that you have a
irritable and apply get a you have the
ability to smash values together
with your and
but you know that the arguably actual
values that you use preparer don't
matter
and seattle
so gavel
applicable bunker
hierarchy is how you value can derive
everything except the tether
yes that in this cut in this case in
practice i have a sellable class that's
as sites market on a uh...
it stated that has built no prob other
than me
and i actually abuse those classes to
make
on his number come in and i didn't get
the job here like there's backward and
forward but like reverse it reversal
aural and or s letter
or a drummer or or i gather or a portly
other they'll turn like melissa of all
the things that's going to visit
services in the opposite order
u_n_ brought restrict actually knows
actually wind up being
kind of like acquitted friend former
client like that with that but i don't
know
also actually abuse back last thing that
i had to do so that i could get better
tigers
uh... to make
a lot of very generic company allotment
yeah i'd say it's really just how we
instantiate applicants richard but i
doubt that that use
how these things that are operating that
that's how we get
i guess they've sort of alcock
overloading that makes lansdale
yet of the deadly whether or not it's
allowed to be any model under any value
it has to be a particular value
uh... and then i get that these are
actually all implemented by class with a
couple getting which is
reserved for heads up
well i tell ya personnel
whole arm
there is there is a that notion of
strength of a of a cover contra strong
and haskell so that we abuse very could
not be able to patient
um... of lending here abuses the
strength of reconquer nasco
so one way to construct a prism is to
abuse sco strength
of of certain bunkers that allow you to
go search for
uh...
weaken left dike an a in a half would be
to uh... apathy and b
ever ever every pondering cast list
right
uh... because the way the advocate
environment
um...
not every quarter and haskell is coastal
blog post on strict discussed right
i think it's driving trek from waiting
that sort of like that not
not
on what i'm talking about dot com
now though at least explain the fact is
buckled up
account of the that um... the constraint
proper driving for them
uh... because we don't have potential
i'll read
though a
um...
he he was
sort of the theoretical side of
um... for them so i drive them one way
just from like reading about them really
are not matter in writing respectable
them the conversion exacting definition
so we were very happy that we got
i feel like i was one two three we could
drive lost like four five always welcome
the same laws
uh... only had one more
warlock theory
millwall
it no
uh...
well thank you